hello everyone it is
September 30th 2022 and we're in cohort
2 meeting number five we're having our
second discussion on the chapter two of
the textbook
so
um we'll jump in shortly to the
questions
but first just wanted to um
highlight a stream that'll be happening
later today
which is number 49.0 and I'll I'll share
in the chat here
um or you can find it through the live
stream page
this is uh with Ali and Jacob who are
here and the upcoming two weeks will
have Dalton sakti of the devil
coming to discuss the paper and this
paper is um it's quite an opus
and we we had a lot of fun preparing for
it
all right
so we'll go to the questions and I think
these are all just great beginning
points is there anyone who wants to
point to a question that they're
interested to begin with
or a question that they asked or one
that they feel has like a a natural
starting point
otherwise I can pick one
uh Daniel the um the question on
thinking between cognition
and thinking was one that I put there it
was just from the the beginning of the
chapter
um a little quote
um my thinking is first and last and
always for the sake of my doing
it's just when you read I always get
confused between cognition and thinking
and knowing and all those sort of
uh words and uh their relationships to
each other so I was just wondering if we
could just sort of clarify that a little
bit
all right what does anyone think
are these terms synonymous
or are different things being pointed at
with different um
terms like this
well I would maybe say that thinking
could be interpreted as action
and no knowing maybe
um
could be a consequence well
knowing could be the specific
representation of beliefs
in the brain
and then cognition is
I see that as the kind of uh
overarching blanket
well thinking is Ali
you know actually there are many
different angles that we can
uh tackle uh the conceptual differences
between these three terms I'm going to
start from the last term knowing uh well
in epistemology the standard definition
for knowing is Justified true belief so
if we take that as a definition of
knowing then we can go to
thinking as the act of gaining that
justified true belief as Jakob has
mentioned some people
describe thinking in terms of action and
then cognition is a kind of
uh a conscious state in which the
thinking happens uh I mean if it's not
the action of thinking per se it's uh
the blank it's the situation or uh the
state in which these kind of thinkings
and knowings happen
but uh obviously the this is a very
simplistic uh distinction between them
they're very nuanced uh discussions
going on in the philosophy of mind uh
about the differences between whether uh
are there are these three concepts
mutually exclusive or they can be
related in a kind of hierarchical way to
each other so
awesome very uh deep answers
one other take would be thinking is uh
gerund verb it's a process
whereas cognition is a
noun
and just from a sentiment perspective
thinking seems to imply like a process
and perhaps the experiencer
like the subconscious regulation of
blood pressure might not be considered
thoughtful or thinking
whereas especially
um as cognitive theories
are kind of pervading
all areas
in a in a type of like pan cognitivism
then cognition is a bit more neutral
with respect to
phenomenology and awareness
so one could say a computer is doing a
type of cognition the sand pile is doing
a type of cognitive process
um this membrane is doing cognition it's
equalizing the temperature like those
can all be described cognitively
and especially as we take active
inference which is a framework derived
in the neurosciences
where these terms might have the least
space between them
but then the question of whether a
computer is doing thinking or knowing
is perhaps a further afield whereas to
say that a computer is doing cognitive
process or information processing
might be less controversial
like extended cognition
but then I guess we just don't hear as
much about extended thinking or extended
knowing
but when they're all
um in our body you know then
these seem to have like the most
synonymy
my cognition is first and last always
for the sake of my doing
okay any other like thoughts or comments
on this question
all right let's kind of can oh yeah
Roman
I just want to just say it so it sounds
as if it's something that's sort of
still in a
in evolution or in just under discussion
is it really still
under investigation or attempting to
find Clarity in these in this language
I mean I like I like that I like that
thinking's the verb and that's that's
sort of where I was uh the direction
that I was
was having with thinking that it's a
that it's an act
uh that's that's my sort of take on it
and cognition is more of the overriding
blanket
um so yeah so thank you for that that's
good
yeah
and um we might be able to find
coherence like in our own understandings
or within the active inference ontology
but the
a larger scale historical Arc around
these topics as well as like
non-english versions of related topics
that's probably more like a
philosophical or maybe even like
theological domain kind of just Trails
off but within these terms as used
in active inference
it may be possible to have a lot more
clarity
especially around like cognition
you know for the purposes of this model
we're defining cognition as the
information processing between input and
output not saying that's the only
definition just like if if one is to say
that's what I mean by cognition
there doesn't need to be
um a qualia
but then somebody else if their
definition of thinking or knowing is
going to be related to equalia
and not like information processing
then that's going to be verging into a
different area
mm-hmm
okay
so let's kind of continue on this
uh broad an important theme
how does active inference fit in with
neuroscience
does anyone who asked the question or
provided some of this
answers and discourse want to give a
thought
okay yeah I asked I asked the question
um
great this is yes what are we actually
doing here are we doing Neuroscience or
are we doing machine learning
um
I think it's some sort of combination of
both but when we when we're talking
about things
do we have a
we have some guidance of what we're what
we're talking about
uh
it seems as though the original
variation of free energy
fits in with the biology there's there's
some correspondence with the physical
of the brain
um related to superficial pyramidal
cells or whatever
um the expected free energy seems so
much like reinforcement learning and
quite away from the neuroscience
great thanks for the comments and ideas
does anyone wanna
add
or or speak to these
faces Ali thank you
yeah
let's say uh about I mean FTP literature
before 2019 uh was mainly concerned with
uh the neuroscientific descriptions of
the mind uh using this active inference
framework but from around 2019 things
have changed and a lot of research are
going on
which try to relate
um
active inference framework to other
areas in physics in economics in even
climatology or other kinds of phenomena
which can be modeled using fvp slash
active inference framework so uh I I'd
say that in the currently the active
inference
framework is just uh is or at least it
converges to be a kind of modeling
framework or a kind of mathematical
structure which would Encompass all can
potentially encompass
many different modeling Frameworks in it
so uh yeah that's the current uh status
of the research
an active inference it's not solely
focused on neuroscientific descriptions
of the Mind
awesome thanks Jacob
yeah I would maybe uh add to the point
that Neil mentioned that
um sometimes it feels like it's
neuroscience and sometimes it feels like
it's reinforcement learning I think
um
I would think more about active
inference as a kind of on the on the
same level as like thermodynamics and
physics where the specific model is not
necessarily that important although we
are assuming we are in this kind of
Bayesian scheme but reinforcement
learning has also been applied to
modeling uh the role of dopamine in the
brain so in a sense we could say if we
if we put it in the in that context we
could say that reinforcement learning is
also related to Neuroscience even though
it's uh
also used in other contexts so
I guess
I'd say that active is
again this kind of overarching blanket
that covers multiple areas
um but it's not necessarily one or the
other
awesome
all right I'll add a few more thoughts
and then anyone who
that's a comment so first this is going
to be a slide from later today uh in
live stream 49.
and it's a Maxwell ramstead tweet thread
you know hashtag scholarship in 2022.
and Maxwell describes first wave free
energy models which didn't have policy
per policy selection per se
the Dynamics of internal and active
States also known as particular States
because that's like the moving particle
it's like the internal States and the
blanket make up the particle and then
the autonomous states are the internal
States and the action States those are
the ones like under Direct Control
whereas you can't directly control your
sensory States but they're still part of
your particle so
there was a gradient descent happening
on the autonomous States
so it was kind of a one-step model and
hence couldn't really be said to
entertain policy selection
counterfactuals planning as inference
and so that was like very much a
variational free energy framing
and that's totally consistent with a
wide range of previous Bayesian work on
gradient descent variational
autoencoders the variational Bayesian
methods all of that area
second wave models starting around 2012
equipped agents with beliefs about State
transitions especially sensory
consequences of movement
the emphasis on the sensory outcomes of
action
has been linked by others to perceptual
control theory
and also Bridges towards embodiment
this enables the design of models with
proper policy selection that evaluated
average free energy expected under each
policy
then third wave models use recursive
expected free energy functional which
enables some more advanced
uh
modeling tools like counterfactuals
so that is one angle
another angle and and so the the
question was spot on with kind of
beginning with Neuroscience if we go to
Carl friston's Google Scholar page
his most cited work and
the work that makes him the most cited
neuroscientist alive slash ever
you'll find although the free energy
principle 2010 paper
has been cited as like a keystone
Fe paper
almost all these several tens of
thousands
are related to methods
related to statistical parametric
mapping SPM
which is arising from the welcome
Imaging Center at the University College
in London and the Decades of Carl and
others work in neuroimaging
basic research and the tool development
around it
so coming out of this framework where
they were doing
uh time series modeling like dynamical
modeling on
hidden State inferences on spatial data
like you're getting the MRI data but
then you're inferring the neural
activation that gives rise to this
as mediated by like sensor and various
sources of
stochasticity
the generality of that framework
especially in light of some
philosophical contributions
by
uh well
in in some ways since 2010 since 2005 to
Kristin was already going for this sort
of
across domain applications of free
energy and so
um
another
um kind of related
like potentially extremely formally
related but just in its scope is like
the constructal law by Adrian Bajan and
other works like that like looking for
patterns across systems
um
and then as Ali mentions that scope Was
Then followed up on with people working
towards specific applications in
different areas
and then now that there's been such
developments with the software packages
and mathematical advances and and
formalisms
that's where we see the encompassing of
a lot of different modeling Frameworks
this is a great question too how should
we be thinking of active inferences
relationship with the way we think the
brain actually works
chapter 5 is going to be
um
about that it's going to be focusing on
specific neural systems like the spinal
reflex arc and also like
um uh
cortical processing
and
there's some there's going to be a lot
of fun discussions on that because
there's kind of like a map territory
issue like if you use a linear
regression on the brain no one thinks
the brain is a linear aggression
but if you use octave inference on the
brain
what is it that makes people think that
something is being done with the map
that isn't just a neural model
like in SPM no one said well the brain's
a statistic parametric map because we
use the SPM package
yet it can feel like people are using an
active inference model
and the claims that they derive are this
is the brain doing active inference
but isn't that kind of like using the
SPM package and then saying that the
brain is doing SPM
so these are really important questions
one other note would be
the um
the structure of Neuroscience
in terms of interacting and nested
information processing units
is a natural fit
for how active inference enables
modeling of interactions and nesting of
information processing units
any other
thoughts or questions on this area
all right yeah yeah thanks thanks uh for
clearing that up I'm looking forward to
chapter five then oh awesome yeah all
right
let's look at we so these look like
there's some surprise
related questions
and then we have some questions on
free energy
Okay so
are the conditions
in conditional probabilities
so regarding the conditions in
conditional probabilities are they
mostly subjective objective or something
else
we may have explored it last week
um
models in their construction are prior
dependent even in figure 2.1
requires are necessarily
multi-perspectival
is there anything anyone wants to like
add
the the conditions are conditioned upon
by the modeler
this is kind of like a map territory
distinction
like in the writing of the expression
the vertical line means that the
modeler's conditioning the first part
upon the second part
and then the question of in the Real
Worlds whether something is conditioned
upon
is kind of the difference
between the map and the territory
but
is there any other like area to explore
here
okay
what are some examples of the difference
between natural
psychological surprise
and Bayesian surprise
okay
so let's think about those two surprise
definitions
the first notion of surprise and they're
both going to be measured in information
theoretic units
the first type of surprise
is just the word Surprise by itself
and it is how surprising a given
observation is
so if the classroom height is four feet
plus or minus one you're going to be
minimally surprised with four feet
observations and you're going to get
more and more surprised as the
observations get further from four
that is what is described in this column
this takes in an observation
and then it contrasts that observations
difference with respect to the
parameterization of whatever family of
distribution is being modeled
and then that tells you how surprising
any given observation is given how a
distribution is set
the second notion of surprise is
Bayesian surprise and that's referring
not to how surprising a data point is
but how far
that data point updates the distribution
so depending on how fixed you are in
your priors you could imagine a super
surprising data point
with zero Bayesian surprise
because it doesn't move the distribution
at all but it was super surprising
and then conversely you can imagine a
data point that's not too surprising
but it updates the priors to fit it
exactly
now the question
asks about natural or psychological
surprise
so that is connecting to kind of a
experiential or psychological
question
how would anyone relate these formal
concepts of surprise and Bayesian
surprise
to
um natural or psychological surprise
Ali
foreign
interesting example that I think can
illuminate the distinction between these
two kind of surprises
um is the Monty Hall problem uh because
you see uh the result of uh I mean when
we solve the Monty Hall problem
the result is very surprising
psychologically
but not in a probabilistically or
Bayesian terms so
you see in Montreal problems actually is
a very famous
puzzle I'm not sure if everybody is
familiar with that that I'm going to
briefly sketch sketch it out suppose
that we have three doors
uh behind one of which is a prize so and
uh the moderator of the competition
opens up
a non-surprised non-price door and asks
us if we want to change our initial
choice
of which door we want to open so our
intuition says that uh
regardless of
uh before the opening that door and the
after the opening opening the door our
choice would be just one half of the
probability of being a
the price behind one of those doors but
uh if we look at it in terms of the
Bayesian uh Bayesian inference or
Bayesian probability uh we can see that
it's not actually one half but it's
one-third so we would have a month
much a double we can double our chances
of winning if we change our choice after
the moderator opens uh that non-price
door but this is actually a very
surprising conclusion into I mean in the
sense of psychologically surprising and
it has even uh confused uh some of the
most greatest math some of the greatest
mathematicians for example
didn't accept this but finally after
some uh after seeing some computer
simulations of this problem uh he
finally uh well accepted this result but
the point here is uh to Define surprise
in terms of its uh Bayesian
inference is just a kind of mathematical
uh
the price or it's a kind of
probabilistic concept and it doesn't
necessarily Maps uh Isis isomorphically
or one to one to our psychological
surprise
yeah awesome and this is going to come
up again and again in the textbook and
in our work in active inference like
there'll be a variance parameter and
they'll say this is the anxiety
parameter well
is that one in the same
you know does that parameter value
translate and um it's it's a very
general issue in
parametric cognitive modeling
and also about interpretability of
parameterized models
but it's an important one
so
um one could imagine some ways in a
situation specific way
to address this like if you have
participants in an experiment
uh you're you're making a parametric
cognitive model of they're looking at
the screen and stuff
and so you're able to calculate given
what you believe their cognitive
parameters to be
the surprise and the Bayesian surprise
of different stimuli
and then you could ask them just purely
emotionally how surprising
would you say that was
and then you could do some sort of
correlation between the self-reported
psychological surprise
and
the values that you inferred but one can
already see that there's like some
complexity there
for example around the enculturation of
the communication or understanding of
what psychological surprise is
so on the pro side this is a very
tangible and accessible experience that
people basically get what does it mean
to be surprised you know you open the
box and it's not what you thought
how does that relate to Technical and
formal definitions sometimes it's clear
sometimes it's a little unclear
all right and one more surprise related
question all right table two one
why does gaussian surprise not contain a
variance parameter
why a pi product
why not surprise perhaps equals natural
log of the normal distribution of the
mean
of the um the data point observed mu
commonly used for the mean and sigma
commonly used for the variance
um
I think there's a few
ways to explore this
Pi is also sometimes used as a variance
parameter
so this can be seen as like and it's
multiplied I don't think this is pi as
like a um it's not a big pie it's not a
multiplicative
um product like this Sigma is a big
Sigma and so it's a sum over dot dot dot
whereas a lowercase Sigma smaller font
is used as like a parameter so I believe
that the parameterization that the the
notation that they're using for the
gaussian someone please correct if this
is not true
mu is the mean of the gaussian
Pi is the variance
it's Precision yes
yeah and so by using the pie it alludes
to the p and so this is a Precision
weighted
difference
between the observation and the
parametric mean so we do have both of
the parameters of the gaussian
if the observation is the mean
then it's going to be minimally
surprising as the the residual the
difference between the observation and
the mean increases
then it gets
um more surprising
is there more to add on this
I what I I was expecting to see uh any
quote where there's there's a normal uh
the normal normal function is e to the
minus x minus mu over Sigma squared
whatever oh
I would have thought the surprise was
the negative log probability of that
which actually might come out as x minus
mu
I'm talking through to the answer yeah X
to x minus mu over variance
which is x minus mu times Precision
isn't it so yeah now that makes sense
okay just to just to um ask or clarify
does it have to do with the fact that
the surprise
um fancy eye fancy J whatever however
you want to look at it
um fans uh is in
a natural logged scale
so we don't see a natural log or
anything in
the representation because we're already
in that space
yeah yeah uh I think
me trying to explain myself I answered
the question there I think I think it's
because it's yeah you're taking the log
of an exponent so it just yeah and with
pi now being Precision that will make
sense
awesome
that's great yeah cool
okay now let's move to talking about the
generative model and then at the end
we'll explore
what expected and variational free
energy are with respect to generative
models
so are these ideas
about the fit between the internal
generative model and observations
which is variational free energy that's
equation 2.5
and expected free energy that's 2.6
applicable to States other than ordinary
waking States
so Altered States of cognition or
Consciousness such as sleep dreams
sensory deprivation seemingly
disembodied States
sometimes sensation doesn't seem to play
a large role in experience
there's probably a whole
host of
ways to go here
foreign
so one of them is that the modeling of a
generative model
as being continually engaged in
perception cognition action is
applicable whether the input is boring
or what or not
just one note
another one is while sensory deprivation
it doesn't mean your senses are off
it just means that the novelty or the
diversity of stimuli is reduced or
deprived
but you're still having observations
like the camera if it's on is still
getting observations even when the lens
cover is on
there might be boring or not informative
but
um in the sense that we're talking about
observations
one cannot be deprived of observations
without having that sense just removed
um
okay
sleep in dreams if the modeler chose to
do it that way then I don't see any
reason why not and um
sometimes primary sensation
may not seem to play a large role in
experience
however
it's actually Altered States Of
Consciousness that people have used to
explore the role of the generative model
in perception
so an example of that might be the Albus
paper
by Adam saffron
there's there's this one image it's like
it's like very funny
um
[Music]
it's going to start with a person
um like doing a cup of tea
and then they're going to start talking
to aliens
maybe it's in a later paper by
um saffron
uh so okay so here's different brain
regions and the person's like okay I'm
seeing the Apple here's an affordance
these brain regions are being activated
in a certain way and then I look down at
my foot there's my foot
and then that was the that's the medium
or that's the threshold dose of a of a
psychotropic something
then in the in the medium dose
activation patterns are altering the
vividness
and the association amongst different
ideas
um and then
in the extreme doses this is like
there's like
um
different patterns of linking
that are leading to experiences that on
one hand somebody could say Well they're
they're lifted from the sensory
observations
but another way to put it is the ongoing
flow of sensory observations
is being
um
integrated and processed differently
it's leading to a different
self-organized harmonic mode in the
language of saffron
such that the perception the experience
which is what we have
is different
and one like little piece of lore around
the Albus is Carhart Harris who's a
psychedelics researcher in friston wrote
this paper Rebus relaxed beliefs under
psychedelics just relax
and then Adam followed with this paper
Albus it's like well it's not simply
relaxed beliefs
in fact in the hierarchical predictive
processing architecture
some beliefs might be strengthened
like top-down priors
might be strengthened in their impact
and that's why the priors might be seen
like in a in a static field
you still like there might be ways in
which actually top-down beliefs are
sharpened and that's why
sounds could be heard from water
bubbling
or images could be seen
in the static or in the tea leaves
so it's not just like relaxed beliefs
simply it just more generally altered
and that sets up perfectly to go through
equation two five and two six and this
related question
all right
so
we're going to look at equation 2.5 and
2.6
and explore how tractable they are
let's
recall equation 2 5 and 2 6. so first
as always thanks for the Epic work to
the people who who added derivations
and
the natural language descriptions
okay
so what is happening in equation 2.5
what variables are coming into the
picture
and how are they being processed
what is this
F describing
what's the situation where f is Big
what's the situation where f is low
does anyone want to give a thought first
also in these descriptions
the letters are connected to the
ontology terms so just a few that are
important to know is X are the hidden
States
why are the observations
that's one important one
um
another important one is that P and Q
are two distributions
Q is like the posterior updated
distribution
[Music]
does anyone want to add anything on two
five or two six or like
um
we can start to think about what it's
actually doing or calculating
okay so some pieces to note
variational free energy
is not prospective
it's dealing with the real-time
flow of data a single data point in the
presence
and then how that data points
can be evaluated
with respect to the current
parameterization
of that data point
so this is like a function f variational
free energy and it's going to be
bringing two arguments in
those two arguments like the two things
that we need to combine
which they happen to be functions Q is a
function
and so f is called a functional because
it's like a function of a function
so what we need to know to calculate key
to calculate f is
um this variational distribution and the
incoming data point
um
one other thing to keep in mind before
we jump into it is
we talk about like minimizing free
energy but with a negative sign
minimizing and maximizing are the same
so
um we can just think about as minimizing
or maximizing as just like a
relativization procedure
and it turns out that
in this minimization framework free
energy minimization expected free energy
minimization
um are like
the less surprising ones
which are going to be understood to be
the better ones
or more preferable because they're more
consistent with being that kind of a
thing
those are going to have lower values
okay
now just some of the like
um sub functions
fancy e
is an expectation of so we talked about
it previously but this is not like a
future expectation like expected Returns
on investments this is like the
expectation of a gaussian with a mean of
four and a variance of one the
expectation is four
so this is like an average
of some other distribution
in contrast H is an entropy function
the entropy is taking in a distribution
and then
um it is calculating how dispersed that
distribution is
how disordered that distribution is
Ln is the natural log so that's a
logarithm and then the only other kind
of like wrapper here
is this KL Divergence
and so KL Divergence we talked about it
last time as well the two lines are like
the two distributions that the KL
Divergence is contrasting
okay so if we're taking expectations
then
the higher the value
the higher the expectation is this is
just like the average height in the
classroom expectation of the height of
the class
higher expectation
higher internally goes to higher here
for entropy more dispersed is higher
entropy
for natural log it's a transformation of
a number
but they're monotonically related so as
the number gets bigger the natural log
gets bigger too it slows down in how
fast it gets bigger but a bigger number
on the number line is always going to
have a higher natural log
just keep in mind that there's like a
minus sign so it's actually like
the other the other way and then lastly
the KL Divergence if these two
distributions are the same their
Divergence is zero
and when the distributions are
increasingly different this KL term
becomes bigger
okay
anyone want to add a comment in here
yes Ali
and then Giuseppe
uh yeah I just wanted to mention that uh
for I mean for the expected or a
variation of free energy and the
expected free energy uh computations are
not that costly but uh when we come
to
uh Computing uh the priors over over all
the uh policies up to a specific time
Horizon uh that would increase the
complexity I mean it has an exponential
complexity class so that's why some
people have experimented with
um proposing some alternative
implementations for active inference
for example one of which is branching
in time active inference which reduces
this complexity significantly or the
work by Baron millage and so on uh but
yes
I mean the expected free energy or the
variation of free energy
uh
I mean they're not costly per uh by
themselves but
um
when the policy comes along uh that's a
different story
yeah just one quick note and then
Giuseppe um the variational framework is
attractability
increasing move
from the outset
we have a factorized model so it's not
like every variable influences every
variable and what variational inference
does is it actually uses specific
optimizable families of distributions
that are set by the modeler
and takes into account the sparsity of
the variables how they're related and it
turns out that that's actually
um for what it is a very tractable
approach
then
within this variational inference
framework
the F variational free energy is going
to be like
far more computable because all it's
doing is taking in one data point and
then comparing it with the priors
basically
whereas expected free energy is
conditioned upon
counterfactual policies
and so that requires enumerating
policies of a given time Horizon
and then evaluating them relative to
each other
and so while each given consideration is
not that computationally challenging as
Ali mentions the space of possible
policies can be vast so if one has like
four affordances like four you can go up
down left right and you want to consider
a Time Horizon of two
you have 16 policies of time step length
too
but if you wanted to consider policies
of time step length 100
you would have
of course an exponentially increasing
number of possible ways to look and
that's what motivates
um not just the variational approach
which like does kind of as well as we
can within a given policy but also tree
search and selection strategies not
unlike chess playing computers in the
80s
where it was like well we can't just
consider every Branch but if we prune a
branch just because there's one move
that doesn't look awesome we're going to
be doing just local optimization and so
it's always this balance with using
generative models to explore branches
more comprehensively and deeply but not
prune them preemptively in case there's
like you know a sacrifice of a pawn and
then it gets you a castle
so you don't want to discard that move
but as those get more and more sparse
will you sacrifice upon in 200 moves
later you get the castle
it's hard to imagine just from
information Theory perspective how that
needle in the haystack is going to be
found
Giuseppe
um yes now just just a couple of um
of details for the people that are not
too too versed mathematically that the
in the in the equation 2.5
uh one thing to to
highlight is that the expectation of
what is in in square brackets is always
expectation with respect to a specific
probability which is in this case the
the approximate posterior QX so it's a
kind of a if you want a weighted average
but with the weights provided by that
specific probability
so it's an integral but and and also
that entropy is basically the
the average surprise
awesome very nice Point entropy
is average surprise
or we can say it's the expectation of
surprise
um yes yes yeah
so and and this is kind of where we
start to see
some of these um like make it fit well
but don't fit too well
if we can bound you can say I have what
I believe to be
the just all things considered the best
model
because I'm expecting 10 plus or minus
one
and so even though not every single poll
is 10
so I'm getting a non-zero surprise as
I'm pulling you know 9.5 10.5 10.3 9.8
but my model of 10 with an expected
surprise
I wouldn't change a thing about it
that's where variational free energy can
get you
Jacob provided some derivations that
connect the first line
to the second line
so that's one interesting thing to
explore
and a really nice move here that's
highlighted
is
um using some of the the definitions of
the operations of natural logs
to separate them as basically like a a
sum of logs
and for logs adding them is
multiplication and subtracting them is
division
um so that's why like Ln of Q of x minus
Ln of P of X can be written as Ln of Q
over p
and then this the expectation
of the natural log
of a distribution divided by another
distribution
is the definition of the KL Divergence
so that's where the KL comes from
actually
um so that's one really nice
piece to um think about
and then with how line one
gets to line three
one can also Trace
how the variables are kind of being like
split and recombined
and each of these formalizations are
going to have like a slightly different
advantage in certain situations
like entropy you have a term that's only
dependent upon the hidden State expected
surprise
here you have a term with evidence
that's only dependent upon the
information coming in
so this can be seen as actually like
um a constant
with respect to your optimization of
beliefs about hidden States
and so that can even simplify some
optimizations further
um
equation six kind of rhymes with
equation 2.5
the partitionings are different
but you'll find that the operations
which are used
are analogous we see expectations over
belief distributions
we see KL divergences
and we see entropy terms
we also notice that the function or the
functional G
is over policies
because the arguments that are being
taken into account
for expected free energy have to be
the policies and beliefs about those
policies like their consequence on
sensory
um outcomes
and that's why almost everywhere you see
it's conditioning on policy
so it's like there's four options
we're going to calculate
a few things and and this will return to
it so
um but one of the key pieces is that
pragmatic value like kind of the the
imperative of pragmatism
is not the maximization
of a reward which is common in reward
maximization and reinforcement learning
but rather it's um going to be about the
reduction of difference
between preferences and observations
all right well
thanks for this
meeting
that was the end of chapter two
in the next two weeks we're going to be
heading into chapter three
that's going to be the high road to
active inference
so chapter two started with like the
Bayes theorem and the frog jumping out
of the hand
here we're going to introduce Markov
blanket formalism and talk about some
imperatives of surprise minimization and
the principle of least action and a few
other things so thank you everybody see
you soon
thank you Daniel